Narrator: It’s crammed with around 55,000 objects on display,
ranging from prehistoric hand axes and a witch in a bottle, to a mask with movable eyes,
and a leaf-shaped dagger.
Narrator: Representatives from Haida Gwaii, a group of islands between Canada and Alaska,
have been in conversation with both the Pitt Rivers in Oxford
and the British Museum in London to improve relationships between the Haida people
and the museums holding their treasures.
For over a century, Haida artefacts have formed an important part of the Pitt Rivers collection.
This includes this Haida war helmet, with its carved and painted octopus,
which the Haida believe was worn by prominent chiefs during battle or ceremonial war dances.
Narrator: All of these items still have huge cultural significance to the local people,
something Haida artists Jaalen and Gwaii Edenshaw felt immediately
when they first visited the Pitt Rivers in 2009.
Gwaii: I didn’t expect it actually, but when I walked into the room with the chief’s headdresses,
it was a very emotional experience for me and, er, it caught me off guard.
You know, those pieces felt like they were…lost.
Narrator: The importance of these items isn’t limited to the objects themselves;
they tell us a huge amount about the cultures they come from.
Take ‘The Great Box’, for example, part of the Pitt Rivers collection since 1874.
We don’t know exactly what it was used for,
but we do know it is a masterpiece of Haida Nation craftsmanship.